[Music]
all right hello and welcome everyone
it's active lab live stream number 45.1
it's june 1st 2022
welcome to the active lab we're a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference
you can find us at the links here on the
slide
this is recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following good
video etiquette for live streams
head over to activeinference.org to find
out more about
what we're up to at the lab and
participate if you'd like to get
involved
we're here in
live stream number 45.1
and we're in our second discussion
around this paper the free energy
principle made simpler but not too
simple
by first in decosta sajid heinz ultofer
pavliotis and par
and the video just like all them are is
a introduction and an invitation
for those who would like to
ask questions in the live chat for those
who would like to join us next week in
the conversation
and just to try to learn and unpack and
understand this paper as well as seeing
it as a starting point for
the continued learning and applying that
we're all involved in
and
we will just begin with some
introductions and overviews
remind ourselves where we've been in
this paper and then start to think about
where we're going
and we'll see who joins
we'll see who asks
questions in the live chat
and i guess where we go together
so we can begin just by giving an
introduction saying hi and mentioning
anything like what's something that
we're excited about what's something
that we liked or remembered about the
paper
and what is something that we're
wondering about or would like to resolve
towards the end of the discussion
so
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california and i'll answer the questions
later how about you blue
i'm blue i'm a researcher in new mexico
and i don't know why i'm tasked with
going first
um
there's there's a lot of things that i
think i would like to
have
resolved or
a greater certainty about
like including
the hierarchical nature of
active inference and how mathematically
that works out
as well as uh like the time dependence
and time independence
um and i'm curious about
uh
like can
i don't know yeah we can get more into
it later
um
yeah
okay
while people are
filing in and getting their questions
ready
let's take a look back at
big question
kind of situate ourselves in this paper
and just recall
also what the main sections are in the
roadmap
so
brock and i worked together on 45.0
and we highlighted the big question just
one way to ask it
as
what are the foundations of the free
energy principle fep
and what does it contribute and then
also we can ask how is active inference
related to fep
and
we
drew from the abstract
where they mentioned starting from a
description of the world in terms of a
random dynamical systems
and ending up with the description of
self-organization
as sentient behavior
greetings carl
all right
how goes it
um i've just managed to get back in my
house after being locked out by my son
but otherwise fine
you found an alternate policy approach
i did and some keys hiding underneath
the bucket
would you say this paper is the key to
the free energy principle or what is the
key
um
this is which ones it's this is the um
the simpler one simple as possible uh
made simpler but not too simple
ah now there are simpler ones
i hope there will be simpler ones so
this is
this is one route to the desired
simplicity
all right so
what
is this paper about
what did you intend to do and how did
you accomplish that in this paper
it was um originally conceived as
a brief summary of the particular
physics paper
if you remember that one that's an
archive
a very dense um
hundred page
deconstruction of
physics as we know it so this was meant
to be a technical
rehearsal and
um
focusing specifically on
the free energy principle in the active
imprints part
and was meant to be as simple as you
could get it but as it was being written
it became more and more complicated so
now we're writing another one that's
even simpler
it was a technical rehearsal then it was
a dress rehearsal and then before you
knew it it was
um
well there's many places to jump in but
first thanks so much for joining and
feel free to join and leave as works for
you
we were interested at the outset with
the layout and the roadmap of the paper
so you described how
there's the introduction and then the
following sections are topically
arranged so
how did these seven
inner
sections
come to be
is that the seven islands in the
island chain are there other
topics how did you come to this order
and these seven sections
right are you posing the question to me
i guess blue could go for it but maybe
you could go first
so i can't see who else is here so i'm
not quite sure
um
who else could speak to this um
so from my point of view um
as the author it was exactly as you say
was the
stations um
on route from
the
basics uh or the basic assumptions of
the free energy principle which is
basically the
launch of an equation
right
right through to the end which is an
account of
uh sentient behavior meant in in a in a
very deflationary way so it was just the
steps that you would need to take
to go from um a laundromat
description of some system
through
to first of all defining
um
systems of interest that had steady
state solutions
and then further
thinking about the nature of thingness
how you would distinguish a thing from
uh something else and the implications
of that distinction as articulated with
a markov blanket
for
the
dynamics and various interpretations of
those dynamics and of course the
interpretation we use
is that of
self-evidencing or gradient flows
that
look as if they are
the kind of gradient flows you would see
in systems representing in a bayesian
sense um
the causes of their sensory inputs on
their markov blanket
and then looking at special classes or
types or kinds of particles in
particular the limiting case of large
particles
where the random fluctuations on the
particular states namely the markov
blanket and their
um internal states
uh tend to zero essentially banished so
such you are now describing things
that have a classical aspect in the
sense that they
um you wouldn't need a sort of
microscopic or quantum
description that they move and behave in
accord with classical or lagrangian
dynamics and that has
um some special put some special
constraints on these gradient flows
on
the lagrangian or the surprisal
that is being read as a gradient flow or
sharing the same minima
as a gradient flow on variational free
energy and that takes us then to the
final move which is
um
what that would look like in terms of
planning as inference and the
articulating that in terms of expected
free energy and then we stopped
awesome
blue anything to add or we can continue
this line
you know i have a question that that's
like a burning question from reading
this paper and listening to carl talk
and then also um doing the textbook
reading group
uh i'm curious about
the language the causes of sensory
inputs
so
and i'm curious about this because you
can see it in so many ways and i know
that it's open to interpretation and
depends upon the model of the system but
as someone from a neuroscience
background like the cause of my sensory
input is like a 450 nanometer light wave
or
um
a pressure wave through air in terms
you know in the sense of sound so when
you think about the cause of the sensory
input like
if there's a red balloon and i'm seeing
red like that's you know 700 nanometer
light wavelength that i'm i'm actually
detecting
but but the then that the balloon is
like missing from that and and so i just
wonder
why did you choose this term or do you
mean it in the literal sense or is it
supposed to be abstracted am i supposed
to you know come away from the cause of
my sense
come away from the red light and go more
toward that's a red balloon
i would come away from the red light and
go more towards the red balloon would
you excuse it for a second but the sun
that lost me out is just knocking on the
door because i stole his keys
thank you
move away from the red light
away from the red light
sorry about that um
yeah no i and so the notion or the use
of the language um causes
um
is used in a
um a very broad sense in terms of
carving up
all variables into causes and
consequences
so very often when you talk in
any modeling context particularly in
terms of
um the inversion of a generative model
people ask what do you mean by inversion
of a generative model well what i mean
is a generative model
is a probabilistic description
of the joint occurrence of causes and
consequences
and usually the consequences are
observable and the causes are not so the
sometimes referred to as hidden causes
um
so
the genitive model provides this um
description of the joint occurrence
probabilistic relationships between
causes and consequences
and the way that we
or the way that one can understand
sensations or sensory samples is as the
consequences of some abstract causes but
because the causes are hidden
and or unobservable
they can only be inferred so these
causes now become random variables that
can only be inferred so it's um from the
point of view of a modeler the forward
model or the generative process would be
a map from cause to consequence
but we only have available or at hand or
on eye
the consequences so we have to do the
reverse mapping which is the um genesis
of the notion of model inversion we have
to map from consequences back to causes
and that's basically the process of uh
bayesian inference so that's where the
language comes from it's just sort of
splitting every the whole universe into
two types of variables causes and
consequences
when you move to the free energy
principle
as articulated in the particular physics
paper
things become a little bit more nuanced
because now you've got the consequences
of external causes impressing themselves
on the mark of blanket but you now also
have internal states internal to the
markov blanket that are now doing the
bayesian model inversion effectively but
the causes are meant as a
a universal and very very high
dimensional
um or referred to
a
a set of very very high dimensional um
variables external states out there that
conspire
through uh whole chains of causal links
to produce the sensory consequences so i
would subsume both the red bloom
and the reflected and irradiant light
and all all of the
biophysics that causes your retinal cell
to fire i that whole chain of causality
will entail a whole series and possibly
uncountable number of um hidden causes
in generating the consequences and you
have to work back through that chain and
and hence the you know the
um the
notion of hierarchical models that
explicitly try to put that chain in
place so one level of your hierarchy
model you have a red balloon and another
level of the model you might have um the
the other consequences of of um that red
balloon in the outside world which would
be um you know reflected light and that
you know passing through your um your
optical machinery and impinging upon
your retina or
you know all of these things will be
implicitly modeled or coarse grained in
your genitive model so that you can
solve the inverse problem reconstruct
the scene out there
given this is how you observed it
because how you observed it um is
specified in the generative model
through a likelihood mapping so if i
knew the cause red balloon you know what
would it what would it feel like how
would i palpate it what would i observe
and that whole likelihood model would
entail all the mechanisms that you know
you described as a sound waves and
pressure waves and uh
and photons and the like uh just to
conclude
another common word or phrase people use
certainly machine learning for this
notion of causes that are unobservable
that they are effectively random
variables because they are the support
of a generative model which is specified
as a probability distribution is hidden
states another word for this is latent
states and i've been told off by some
reviewers for using the word latent
states but i can't remember why so i've
i've reverted to this using them in
exactly the same sense that latent
states or hidden states
are those unobservable variables
um that are distinguished between from
observable states or outcomes or um
measurements or or or data
so that's where the language comes from
that's very helpful
yeah it really helps me um because it's
something that i've struggled with but
to think about it a hidden cause in
terms of a causal chain
that leads to the observation that
that's a very helpful um way for me to
think about it thank you
good yeah and also how hierarchical
nesting of models which we can come back
to it's like one model might be the
unobserved is the temperature in the
room and the observation is the number
on the thermometer but you don't really
see the number you see the light so then
you could have a two step model where
the causes of the temperature
are the
shape of the thermometer and then the
shape of the thermometer is what number
it is and so depending on how much data
and the adequacy that's needed
one could coarse grain and just say
we're going to go from the hidden state
to the observed inferred number or can
start to parse that if there were
degrees of freedom there
let's maybe go through oh did you do
could say that's a nice example but you
know you could have a sort of
a deep
artifact or personal creature with your
actually has the representation of
temperature as a cause of the shape or
the height of the thermometer or you
could have a very um shallow artifact
that just registers the height of the
thermometer and i have in mind here the
difference between a thermostat and me
or you so we would know that you know we
would represent and explain changes in
the shape
um in terms of a change in temperature
because that's our model and we would
have a deep model but the thermostat
might not it might directly act upon the
world simply because the shape you know
there is some quantitative single valued
scalar
observable that is telling it to switch
the radiator on so it's a nice
distinction you know there's no rule
which says how how much course training
or how
much depth or hierarchical structure
you uh bring to the table in terms of
trying to explain what you can observe
great let's go to
quite early in the discussion in the
introduction
um
elsewhere
the tautology in the top logical aspects
and the falsification have been explored
so let's jump into a slightly different
point which is the utility
so there is a rhetoric in the paper is
such a description
of the fep
being in this framework or
principle-like way
and
the answer was probably no
but there was a however
so where do you see the utility of the
fep and how does that come into play
in the particulars
for carl or blue maybe to you first
blue goes first yes blue where have you
seen utility in the fep
i like that the fep
resolves so many
very difficult things to model or
maybe doesn't resolve it fully yet but
has the potential to resolve is maybe a
better way to put it um especially in
terms of hierarchical modeling
also
the balance between exploration and
exploitation complexity and accuracy
so i think that it's useful to
describe circumstances where
there's not always a single solution but
but maybe um
a best solution
or how can we find the best solution
given what we know
okay
what would you say carl where what was
the function of this example
with
the principle of least action which
we'll also want to explore but
how is their utility in the fep
how is their utility in the principle of
least action and what is their
relationship between fep and the
principle of leased action
i think that uh blue uh you know has
provided the answer um
and it can be illustrated with
hamilton's principal release principle
of least action so
if i
wanted to understand um how a ball um
was thrown or understand its dynamics
since kinetics and it's you know the
laws the physical laws
by which a ball or a massive uh body uh
pursued a particular trajectory
then what i could do is to apply
hamilton's principle of least action
to the particulars of this situation the
mass of the ball the initial conditions
the um the wind resistance and
everything else that i would need to
know
in order to predict the behavior and
understand the mechanics that underwrote
what actually unfolded
so um if you sort of dumb down
blues
aspiration to understand sentient
creatures and and
uh you know
the distinction or the relationship
between exploration and exploitation and
just think about understanding the
trajectory of massive bodies what you
will end up doing is appealing to
a principle of least action and all that
says is these prescribe
the
um the lawful behaviors
if you apply that principle to a
particular situation so for us as
builders of um sentient artifacts or
neuroscientists um trying to understand
um sentient creatures
what it says is that you have a
principle at hand that allows you to
build
and if you can build an artifact that
either resembles or reproduces the kind
of behaviors that you're interested in
studying then you have a more formal
understanding of the mechanics and how
those
how those artifacts or systems that
actually operate or you can simulate um
or you can build um
um artificial intelligence
systems you know so
it's all in the pragmatic building of
something
by applying
the free energy principle to something
and you may be asking what is that
something well it's a generative model
so all the hard work starts
not in understanding or deploying the
free energy principle you know it's all
the hard work is really specifying
writing down the generative model apt to
describe the kind of creature you're
interested in or that you're the the
system
um you're trying to characterize and
understand i'll just close by
um
nodding to or giving a nod to richard
feynman here because that that whole um
the motivation for application of the
png principle and in a sense the
motivation for the free energy principle
in and of itself
was just to
um
realize or provide tools for realizing
the
observation that was famously or
purportedly on his blackboard at the
time of his depth that if you can't
build something if you can't create it
you can't understand it so to build it
is to understand it and vice versa
great
um i'll ask one follow-up on findman and
then we have a great question in the
chat
what is variational inference as feynman
utilized it and as it's utilized in fep
and active
right well variational inference
is generally read as
a suite of
data analytic tools called variational
bays
that used to always also be called
ensemble learning but i haven't heard
that phrase um in in the recent years so
what is variational base well it's um a
form of approximate bayesian inference
um which should be contrasted with exact
bayesian inference so what's the
difference between approximate and exact
bayesian inference the key difference is
that you
assume a functional form
for
the posterior beliefs that you're trying
to
update from your priors to the posterior
beliefs now in assuming a functional
form
you are going to depart from the actual
true posterior and it's that departure
which renders the inference scheme an
approximate bayesian inference scheme
but what you buy
for that approximation
is tractability
so exact bayesian influence cannot be
realized physically
by which i mean it's mathematically
intractable
and also numerically impossible to do
exactly
even if you have enormous sampling and
you use sampling based procedures like
metropolis hastings or
gibbs sampling
just open brackets is another way of
approximating a post area just with lots
of some with a large
number of samples and sample density
so
what what what's what's the fundamental
importance of the move from exact basin
influence to approximate bayesian
inference namely variational inference
it's because you've assumed a functional
form which makes your inference
approximate
you can now
analytically
convert what is an impossible
marginalization or integration problem
uh into a tractable
optimization problem so just put some
flesh on that um
if you wanted to use um if you wanted
well let's take richard feynman's
problem
he was trying to work out the
probability distributions over
all the paths a small particle could
take from some initial state to some
final state
now
given the nature of the paths he had in
mind
there is a universe of an an enormous
and countable number of such paths
which meant that any um either analytic
or numerical realization of these paths
meant that the it was impossible
to
normalize the distribution by
marginalizing or integrating over the
distribution to work out the
normalization constant also known as a
partition function which you would need
in order to specify the probability
distribution
so when people talk about an intractable
marginalization or integration problem
what they mean is for very high
dimensional probabilities it is
you cannot
integrate under the unnormalized
distribution to produce a probability
distribution however
if you know the functional form
then you can create
what's called an evidence bound
or a variational free energy
which is always
um
for a physicist always greater than
the
um
the quantity that you want to estimate
or marginalize
the the the evidence
that constitutes the result of that
marginalization also called the marginal
likelihood
which means if you can reduce that bound
you're guaranteed to find the minima
that is um always greater than the thing
you actually want to minimize which is
usually the negative log marginal
likelihood
which converts an impossible integration
problem into tractable optimization
problem and that's conceptually quite
important
so what it means is that you
are now converting
effectively an inference problem an
exact base in inference problem
into an optimization scheme so now you
have a formal definition of um the
normative account of behavior you can
now talk about inference as an
optimization procedure where you're
optimizing a well-defined objective
function that is the variation of
freehand and why variational well very
simply
given the functional form
of your approximate posterior
and given the functional form of the
bound um on the marginal likelihood or
the negative log marginal likelihood to
be more precise
and you then use
the calculus of variations
to demonstrate that this is indeed a
band and thereby you can perform a
gradient descent or you can find the
minima
analytically
as part of that optimization scheme so
the variational base just means you're
using the calculus of variations
to
um
license the use of
a particular approximation to the
posterior
excellent
welcome thomas thank you for joining
would you like to
say hi or give any overview i can
continue with the question or please
feel free to take it in any direction
um well thank you for inviting me um
i i don't have any particular comments
at the moment because unfortunately i
missed the start of it apologies that i
joined late um
perfect well
i'll go to the question that was in the
chat so this was
asked by jax in relationship to our
discussion about the balloon example and
the thermometer example with hidden
causes and observed consequences
is this all in the service of
homeostasis
so how can we connect what we've been
talking about with this causal bayesian
framework
and the variational inference to the
idea of homeostasis and survival for
cognitive entities
as per tradition we could go to blue
or thomas if you'd like to jump in on
that
no please go ahead
you have to give thomas a few minutes to
settle in
yes
i'm deflecting that question back to you
so you've judged every question so far
today so we're going to let daniel
answer this one
sure
so just to give a first thought
so we just heard about how variational
free energy calculation is converting an
impossible integration problem to
attractable optimization and a gradient
descent that's through time
and so
if we were trying to stay within
homeostatic bounds for temperature or
for blood sugar or some other vital
parameter
and we found ourselves anywhere but
exactly on the one target location so
we're some divergence away from a set
point
the number of paths that we could take
back to get to our set point or to get
to the
range of comfort
just like feynman's particles the number
of pods we could take would be infinite
like in the blood sugar example you
could change the regulation of every
single gene in every single possible
combination so the number of paths and
microstates would be very large
variational inference and planning as
inference
would give us a way to
in an unfolding through time way
functionally optimize and return to
homeostasis
rather than waiting on the sideline for
this intractable
integration to occur
we could start moving in a direction
that's more like a ball rolling to the
bottom of a hill
or like a molecule descending to a gibbs
free energy attractor
but in some
other space
that we're doing inference in
maybe blue next
we'll go from least knowledge to most
because um
i don't know homeostasis i think there's
always um
so we started off by saying
um
what exists or if you exist what must
you do right like so the paper starts
off saying this way so if something
exists what does it what must it do
rather must what must something do in
order to exist so it starts with the
reverse of this and i think homeostasis
is like the most
driving
force behind life
which goes back to the life as we know
it paper
and also a particular physics
so so what must something do in order to
exist something biological must maintain
this non-equilibrium steady state
density of homeostasis because if you
don't then you die so equilibrium in a
living system is death
and so fundamentally i think that
it does come back to
homeostasis um
yes
thomas
sure i i think i've got my bearings now
um
so
i think homeostasis is always quite an
interesting
comparison with or thinking to relate
back to variational inference and the
free energy principle
um and i think for me part of the reason
for that is that homeostasis is really
just the observation that sense of
values tend to live in some particular
space over time or some particular
distribution
and so it's more
when you talk about homostatic bounds
what we're talking about really are just
um
the
description of how things tend to be
um
and
coming back to this question about
inverting this question of how how
things have to exist and going
in reverse and saying well it does exist
and it exists in this form how does it
then do it
um
we're sort of starting when we talk
about homostasis from the principle that
we are in this range and traditionally
you then talk about negative feedback
type mechanisms reflexive
um correction of deviations from some
set point
but you could also see that as exactly
the process of
um maintaining some steady state density
over time of climbing probability
gradients exactly as you would for
a
variational inference
um
and
when you look at things in that
framing then and and particularly
because in homeostasis we're normally
using sensor values whether those be
vary receptors or
um measures of
glucose control and sorry blood glucose
and that sort of thing
and we're really dealing with a
probability distribution over some sort
of sensory data here predominantly
interceptive data
um which
is effectively a marginal likelihood
once you then equip it with a model of
how those sensor variables are are
generated
and so one of the things that's useful
in terms of taking it from homeostasis
to variational inference or putting it
in the realm of the free energy
principle is it then asks you to
try to formulate the sort of generative
model you'd need
to be able to explain those data and
therefore to to
optimize your your own internal
environment
um and that's i think where a lot of the
interesting neuroscience comes in where
you try to build the models that the
brain might use
um and then invert as the process of
performing autonomic reflexes and the
like
one
thank you
carl anything to ask or we can continue
with other questions
no i did just very briefly just to
reinforce the last two answers you know
the question is an excellent question
because in a sense the free energy
principle is just about describing
things that have a generalized
homeostasis
so it's not saying how would you
implement homeostasis it's saying that
our universe seems to be populated with
things that possess a homeostasis so
what behaviors must they what principles
must they conform to
so you know it's a
a very good question
in this notion of
generalization
we just heard generalized homeostasis
and i'd like to ask how it's connected
to two other generalized
generalized synchrony and generalized
coordinates of motion
and if there's any other generalizations
we can add those but
how might this notion of generalized
homeostasis
be related to generalized synchrony
for one entity or in communicating
ensembles
and then the notion of generalized
coordinates of motion
shall i take that one
sure
um well sure i take that one first i
think there's a very close relationship
between the notion of generalized
synchrony and the notion of a
homeostasis um and by generalizing i
just mean the same tendency to keep
states that matter sometimes referred to
as essential variables in the
cybernetics literature within certain
bounds or within viable domains
if you wanted to describe that process
as a
systems dynamical systems theory what
you would be saying is that the
trajectories through some state space
are limited to a relatively small
attracting set and the smallness of that
attracting set um defines the bounds or
the range that characterizes that
particular system so um for you and i we
have quite narrow bound say on our
temperature um
and that just means that our dynamics
keeps us within or close to
those set points um so from the point of
view of the
um the dynamicist
understanding
the the
dynamical behavior of two systems that
are coupled to each other these can
either be
um
a creature or a particle and it's
embedding niche or environment or the
external states or there could be two um
similar uh particles in dyadic
interaction
the way that if they are coupled and
they are both restricted to a small step
set of states or paths at the um
relative to the the total number of
states or paths that they could
pursue or occupy
then they're said to have a generalized
synchrony um technically it means that i
can predict how i will move
given your state and vice versa
so i think there is a very close formal
relationship between the notion of
generalized synchrony and um and
homeostasis of the kind that is uh
accountable to the coupling between um
one system and another system
generalized course of motion
um i think um are meant in a slightly
more technical sense so in order to
understand the dynamics
so to move from a description of things
in terms of where they are in some state
space say your temperature and now to
understand the processes that keep you
at a certain temperature then you have
to talk about the rate of change of
temperature or the paths
in a state space where one dimensional
coordinate of that state space is
temperature
so how would you describe mathematically
paths well you could just have a long
list of
states as an increasing function of time
or there's a more compact way of
describing a path
which is effectively to use a taylor
expansion
and and describe it with a list of
coefficients of that taylor expansion
which turn out to be
the state you're in at the moment
your velocity
your acceleration your jerk and all
higher order temporal derivatives
and if you go to an infinite number of
temporal derivatives you can now
reconstruct using that taylor expansion
your trajectory into the future and into
the past so generalized coordinates of
motion are just the observation that you
have to in describing or most precisely
in defining the support of a
probabilistic description of a system
if you want to describe the paths then
you just
augment the state with all its higher
order uh
temporal derivatives
and that's called generalized um
coordinates of motion
interestingly should be slightly
disambiguated from the way that people
use generalized coordinates um in
physics
so that's usually read as basically
thinking about a complete description of
the system just in terms of the first
the state and its first order temporal
derivative so you'll come across for
example in um
mechanics um
p and q so
momentum and position um
so uh if you're in quantum physics
you'll be dealing with real and
imaginary parts of your particular
variable
um or a probability distribution um
the the important observation here is
that you've got more than one variable
to describe what's going on uh and this
if you like is the simplest kind of
generalized points of motions is
basically x and x prime or rate of
change of x or x dot but you can extend
that notion and infinite uh to create a
hilbert space or an interdimensional
space where one point in this infinite
dimensional space
encodes or stands in for mathematically
represents an entire trajectory or or
path and that's a formalism that in fact
the free energy principle is actually
articulated in in terms of um path
integral formulations
awesome
thomas would you like to add anything
there
it's difficult to know what to add in
such a comprehensive description
um
i suppose one thing i'd pick up on this
um and perhaps this is more a question
for carl but um you mentioned the idea
that taylor expansion is a more compact
way of describing the trajectory
um i was wondering whether that's
necessarily true i appreciate it would
be if the trajectory is relatively
simple um but
you you could argue that you need a very
large number of taylor coefficients to
be able to adequately describe a more
complex trajectory
um complex in the sense of non-linear
and whereas a
um
whereas it may be simpler in some
circumstances just to have a series of
discrete temporal points
yep excellent question so yeah so
you know it speaks to
when i when i or people like me talk
about compact we're sort of
implicit in that
statement is the notion of some
truncation um and certainly one
truncation of the kind uh you just
mentioned would be um having a discrete
set of points but if you wanted to
represent the entire path
you're obliged to
write down an infinite number of numbers
you can either write an infinite number
of states as
time moves forward or backwards or you
can write down an infinite number of
taylor taylor coefficients or
generalized coordinates of motion
so
you certainly generalized course of
motion in and of themselves
don't afford any compactness but the
when you when you actually apply these
different kinds of representations uh
practically speaking
then
there are two kinds of truncations that
now um
present themselves if you're dealing
with continuous time trajectories so
that your path is now described as a
function of time you normally have to
truncate it by specifying t equals zero
and some horizon in the future you know
the initial and the final state so
there's a choice there that you have to
make in order to deal um practically or
numerically indeed in some instances
analytically
with a path by truncating its length in
time
the equivalent truncation in generalized
coins of motion is in terms of a
discrete bound or upper limit on the
number of the um the number of the uh
generalized coordinates or order of the
temporal derivatives the nice thing the
compactness um
comes
in generalized coordinates in that
there's a natural
space in which you can do that
truncation and that comes from the fact
that as you increase the order of the
temporal derivatives or the order of the
uh generalized coordinates of motion
because
the
variance of the random fluctuations
on the higher order motion
gets
large very very quickly
you can um assume that after a certain
number of generalized coordinates or
orders of generalized quants of motion
the precision is effectively zero
so that means that you can get away
with in describing an infinitely long
trajectory
with
a small number of generalized
coordinates because there's no further
information in the higher orders so it
now becomes like a local uh description
but
and in that locality um
it um
it becomes compact in the same way that
you would discreetly
change the length of the time series or
the path um in a sort of
in a function of time formulation um so
practically what tends to happen um and
it has to happen in the sense that the
random fluctuations have to be fast
therefore they have quite a narrow
autocorrelation function and that um
the shape of the autocorrelation
function determines how quickly the
precision of higher order motion
decreases so generally speaking um even
for quite smooth random fluctuations um
you don't need or generalize orders of
motion beyond about four to six orders
of motion so just practically speaking
um then you now have a compact
representation but in doing that
truncation
you now can no longer
roll out the path using the taylor
approximation to t equals infinity
you can only roll it out
with confidence for a for a relatively
shorter period of time it's not defined
precisely because of course you're
you're defining it probabilistically
because you've got random fluctuations
in play
so it has a sort of soft locality
associated with it but only when you do
the truncation
awesome
i'll ask a follow-up on the taylor
series
especially in spm
the statistical parametric mapping
there's discussion of the volterra
series so what is the volterra series
how is it different from the taylor
series
and what
are they doing
does blue want to take the social thomas
again
i i can have a go but i think that's a
bit before my time being involved with
spm on the whole and
as i understand it it's more a
kernel-based representation of dynamics
where
you're looking at convolution um with
particular kernels over time as an
expression of how dynamics might evolve
beyond that i think i'll probably have
to refer back to carl to to answer that
one in any detail
and let's go
i'm asking to understand a little bit of
the history of the movement from
focusing on the taylor and the volterra
to only seeing the taylor series in the
current paper we're discussing
so but thomas is uh absolutely right the
the volterra series is a way of
describing um
convolution operators that are an
equivalent description of your equations
of motion in terms of convolutional
kernels of increasingly high order uh
but daniel you're you're also absolutely
right um implicitly
in the sense that a volterra
kernel expansion
just is
a functional taylor approximation to any
given dynamical system
so
what's the difference between a taylor
expansion of a path of a function
and a functional
a functional
approximation and it
it just
it's using exactly the same technology
but now um exp
expanding the uh or applying the taylor
approximation to the equations of motion
so the functions
that determine the flow of the system so
you're applying a taylor approximation
to the flow operators or the equations
of motion but the spirit of the
expansion is exactly the same as a
standard uh taylor expansion um
i don't think we need to know much more
about it really in the sense that um
the volterra series expansion is another
way of providing a compact description
compact in the sense you truncate the
taylor expansion um
in the same way we were just describing
truncating the order of generalized
coordinates of motion to get a compact
representation and in some instances a
compact um
inversion scheme so normally um when
people actually apply and certainly as
we apply in a practical data analysis
context volterra series we generally
don't worry about um very high order
terms and in fact all our subway is
written just to deal with first and
second order terms so we actually stop
at the second order um second order
derivatives or functional derivatives um
which is you know even simpler than
the uh you know
stopping at the fourth on the sixth
order in terms of expressing the
original variables in generalized
coordinates of motion
but because it's really a device
um
that just re-represents
a
differential equation
in terms of convolution operators and
kernels it doesn't really get you
anywhere in terms of understanding the
mechanics or the theory behind it so
there is nothing in the free energy
principle that refers to
the volterra series expansion but you
could always um derive a monterey series
expansion and the implicit kernels to a
certain order given some differential
equations um that you know at hand and
if those differential equations are
doing a
um
a gradient descent on free energy such
as in a bayesian filter you could always
articulate a bayesian filter in terms of
a convolution operator um
you know which might be one way of
understanding um you know how bayesian
smoothing and basin filtering
operates
awesome
we're deconvolving
and adding action
in many many layers and adding more
depth to the deconvolution
and to the planning and inference
so speaking of convolution no i have a
follow-up question that's maybe a little
bit convoluted or hopefully i can
articulate articulate it well
so when we're talking about in in the
very beginning of the paper um
you talk about the focker planck
equation and then you talk about the
path integral formation and the the
focus focker plank encompasses
random fluctuations and then the path
integral formulation uh encompasses the
trajectory right of a particle and we
talked about or you talked about the
like fast
path and the slow path and the focker
focker plank is fast and then the path
integral is slow
so i just want to kind of try to wrap my
mind around what happens
like for
atoms inside of my cells okay there the
the density is over states like the
atoms can occupy excited states or or
any number of states
but the cells are are really the ones
doing the work the m the motion is
happening inside of cells so that's kind
of the slow
um
the slow procedure right the path
integral path but then when you think
about the cells they're in my body so
the cells then are occupying the states
and i'm doing the moving around so then
i'm on the trajectory uh um and
similarly like i am in any number of
states with all the rest of the humans
on planet earth all in any number of
like we could be any number of places
but they're all on planet earth and then
planet earth is moving at a slower
trajectory so what is the math kind of
or can can you guess or or maybe
foreshadow how the map
compresses or
unfolds in this kind of hierarchical
situation
so thomas has to answer that one and he
has to use the word renormalization
group
i thought you might say that
i was going to try and do it without but
now that you've said that
um
[Music]
so
just to
to start with i mean you you you
mentioned the the this problem
to start with in the context of the
focal plank equation and the path
integral formulations and and looking at
that sort of distinction
and
which i think is
is interesting when thinking about fast
and slow um but it is to some extent
orthogonal i think it's interesting when
thinking about fast and slow um in that
you you might expect that the
the focal point equation describing the
um rate of change or the evolution of
some probability density
um is going to be a slower evolution
than the evolution of sort of individual
particles that might be described by the
stochastic differential equation or
longevity equation of that system there
may be very fast fluctuations but really
what we're dealing with when we're
dealing with a focal plank equation is
some summary statistics and slower
change over time that might be
reflective of a mean or a variance
that does
link back then into the idea of a
renormalization group
which is a way of describing how things
at one temple scale can be summarized in
terms of um some slower changes and some
faster changes
typically the way you might do that in a
dynamical system setting would be to
look at the the jacobian which is a
linearized version of the um of the flow
equation
um and look at the
eigenvalues and eigenvectors flow and
the eigenvalues tell you how quickly
the system is either expanding or
contracting or how quickly it's um
decaying in one direction or in
unstable systems going off towards
infinity
and that means that if you take the set
of eigen
they will tell you a series of different
directions that the system is changing
in and the speed with which they're
changing
that means that you can you can choose
at some point at which or some threshold
above which the um eigenvalues are
considered slow and below which they're
considered fast and i got that the right
way around i have as long as they're
negative eigenvalues
those eigenvalues are each associated
with an eigenvector which is
just a way of expressing some linear
combination of the components of that
system or
um you could think of it as a direction
in some high dimensional space that
describes the the
position of that system at any one time
by separating things out or separating
out the eigenvectors and the particular
directions based upon whether their
eigenvalues are large or small
you can separate the system out into its
components that move very slowly and
decay very rapidly oh sorry they move
very slowly and those that decay very
rapidly
um
and and that's effectively the principle
that the renormalization group works on
when applied to these kinds of systems
because it then says that if if we have
some way of describing all the things in
that system
we separate them out into the fast and
slow components we can then say well
let's just look at the fast components
find some new way of grouping them
um and then look at the fast components
of that or the slow components of that
and continue separating it out
hierarchically
to
multiple different scales
and that can be quite interesting in a
range of settings to think about the
emergent behavior you might get at
higher and higher levels when the
dynamics the lower level might be might
be a very simple description
um
[Music]
and i think that's probably what you
were getting at when you're talking
about the um the sort of very fast
movement of atoms in your cells versus
the slightly slower movement of of
yourself
and the even slower movement of things
that are much larger and and evolve over
a much larger time scale
you could read each move from one time
scale to the slower time scale as an
application of a renormalization group
operator
is that enough
from your perspective carl have i said
the words renormalization group enough
interesting i just wrote down thomas
when you said thinking about fast and
slow
and that plays into this
meta-bayesian cognitive systems on
cognitive systems angle
any entity might be thinking fast and
slow
famous work but this is thinking about
the fast and the slow maybe of a
cognitive entity and maybe that's
multi-scale
so i'm going to bring another
question into chat and then we'll be
continuing on
what type of boundary does
a markov blanket define for a system
functional in terms of ports
or constructive and modular with
interfaces
or might both viewpoints be considered
depending on modeling reasons
i think for me you may have to unpack
what some of those terms mean a little
bit more um
when you're talking about ports and
and whether they're constructive what
does that mean
[Music]
it was a question from a chat so i'll
try to unpack and see what you think
um
perhaps even a general question would be
what is the physical interpretation of
these markov blankets that are being
identified
are they
causal or functional connections that
occur across an interface
like a usb port
or are they
the interfaces themselves
or in what viewpoints exist to interpret
the markov blanket in terms of the
modeling of some defined system of
interest
it's an interesting question at
quite a few levels and i think you could
probably
you could probably unpack each of those
terms in several different ways
um and
i i guess the first thing to do is think
about how we define a markov blanket and
what it what it actually means because
we can we can sit around interpreting it
in various ways of different sorts of
systems
but actually the key the key thing is
that it's a probabilistic relationship
it's a relationship between
normally three distinct sets of
variables
um
where we're saying that
two of those types of variable are
separated by the markov blanket
probabilistically and all that means is
that
the two that are being separated are
conditionally independent of one another
once we know the thing that's doing the
separating and the thing that's doing
the separating is the markov blanket
and often that means that there are
direct relationships between each of
those things in the blanket but no
direct relationship across the blanket
but then it's important to think about
what sort of relationships we're talking
about whether those are dynamical
relationships and
causal relationships and all sorts of
other other ways you can describe the
interactions between pairs of
states
and
and it's a discussion we've had on and
off for
the last couple of years really about
what is the relationship between
dynamics and
probabilistic relationships and even
which probability distributions are
appropriate to to use to even define a
markov blanket of this sort
um
one answer to that is that we can look
at the markov blankets associated with
some steady state density um
but we can also do the same thing with
any probability distribution which
includes distributions over
um
over the paths and look at the
independence or dependence between
different paths when formulated in terms
of path there's a slightly clearer
relationship between the dynamics of the
system and the markov blanket because
once we've said that the path of one
variable
or two sets of variables are independent
one another given the
[Music]
the truth about the dynamical coupling
and implies a certain degree of sparse
coupling
um between those in a in a dynamical
setting
and so that and it's probably once you
look at the dynamical setting there's a
lot of the
physics
as you've framed it might come in
because you can then start to interpret
that in terms of
physical influences and things that
might cause an acceleration or a
change in velocity or change in position
and interpreted in terms of physical
forces
um
there are um
there are of course other other ways in
which you can look at markup blankets
and sometimes they're interpreted in
terms of sort of cell membranes and that
sort of thing and i wondered whether
that was what was meant when ports were
mentioned because you can think of sort
of iron channels as being ports that
allow interactions
uh between two sets of states i think
when people make those sorts of
comparisons you have to be very careful
about what exactly you mean which
variables reflect um different parts of
that blanket so for instance you might
talk about intracellular extracellular
ion concentrations
and being independent of one another
conditioned upon the state of some
cellular protein
and
so i i think again it's an interesting
question and there are lots of different
ways you could unpack it and you could
think about a range of different systems
and try and interpret what the markov
blanket is there and what the physical
interpretation of that is if it is a
physical system
ultimately i think probably the physics
of it is
going to be articulated most clearly in
terms of dynamical equations
um which sometimes bear a direct
relationship to the mark of blanket but
it depends where it's defined or in what
domain it's defined
awesome
there was two complementary ways
that
this
question one
it's like this is where the two paths
first branched and they're complementary
but
could you
describe
where equation one begins
and read it however you see fit and then
the question mark at the end
and then
help us understand how
the probability density can be expressed
in two complementary ways
what is equation one showing what does
the question mark leave us with and how
do these two sides shown on the left and
the right provide two complementary
approaches
i feel like i've done a lot of talking
but i'm happy to take this one as well
if you if you'd like me to
i'm sure
so the
first line of equation one um we're
really just describing some dynamical
system that
has some fluctuations associated with it
so there's some degree
of
randomness um where that randomness may
be interpretable as deterministic
behavior at a much faster scale that
we're effectively ignoring through the
application of our renormalization group
we were speaking about earlier
and so our x in this equation is this
some variable that's evolving through
time
um the f of x describes
how uh in a deterministic system that
the rate of change of number that
variable um
would depend upon the variable itself
depend upon its position in space
and the omega term at the end here it
tells us that there's some additional
fluctuations associated with that
something that's um changing in a less
predictable way at least at the scale
and speed of description that we're
interested in
the second line of the equation um
provides
a little more definition to that so
the first equality is relating
the
current position of the system the
current x to the
um
the
probability density describing the
fluctuations so saying how that's likely
to be
at any one point
and here we're saying that it's
something that is
zero mean so we if we were to take an
average over time the fluctuation would
end up averaging to zero
um
but then we're also defining a variance
that's the same this is this two times
gamma uh parameter which effectively
tells us about the um
the
amplitude of those fluctuations
the implication symbol then is saying
okay so if we've um
if we've found that
or if we've defined it in this way so we
now know the form of fluctuations that
then tells us the form of the rate of
change of x
um and we know that if the average rate
of change of
um or the average fluctuation is going
to be zero then the average rate of
change of x is just going to be our f of
x so the same
path or the same rate of change the x
would have if we were dealing with a
deterministic system
however we then have this additional
uncertainty around that rate of change
um
which inherits exactly the same variance
as the
random punctuation state
so
we then finally have this this third
line which says so what is
this probability distribution how do we
now account for
um what the distribution of x would be
at some time or um
and i say at some time to make an
additional distinction that isn't
[Music]
necessarily expressed in this slide
which is that
we can talk about the distribution of x
evolving through time from some initial
conditions or we can talk about the
distribution that it will eventually
attain if we if we wait until we're a
long way from our initial conditions
which is then the steady state density
so the point at which the blank equation
here evaluates to zero um
[Music]
so there are several ways now we can we
can think about the distribution of x
and the density associated with it
equation three then says well we could
also look at it a different way and
think about some
distribution or density over alternative
trajectories that x could take in
alternative paths
which is a description of a slightly
different sort of quantity but is um is
equivalent in many ways because they're
determined by exactly the same things
does that sort of make sense i know said
quite a lot there
awesome
have i got myself out of answering the
next question
yes
probably one rain pass
um
maybe we can even just continue walking
through and understanding the formalisms
it's how we structure the dot zeros is
with the formalisms and the figures in
order
and so we we
follow along and try to connect key
points in between
so
um you wrote that both the focker planck
and the path integral formulations
inherit their functional form from
assumptions about the statistics of
random fluctuations in one which we just
described
then
you describe the path of least action
and the most
likely path
so
what is happening in four
where is the fluctuation being reduced
to zero
and what does it mean to take the most
likely path or the path of least action
blue do you want to do this what do you
want me to do
definitely by all means carl why don't
you why don't you go
okay um so just to backtrack a little
bit and just to reiterate some of the
key points that thomas just made um just
notice that the everything basically
starts with this largemouth equation or
stochastic differential equation
and then you can go in one of two ways
you can go via the density dynamics
description of the
of the probability density distribution
which is a description which is
deterministic or you can go by the path
integral formulation and you can map
gracefully between one the other they're
complementary you can derive one from
the other a little bit like the
difference between dealing with the
equations of motion or dealing with the
convolution operators that we're just
talking about they're equivalent in many
senses
however the way that they are used in
the free energy principle are very
distinct so i just wanted to rehearse
that because that speaks to the the
particular question here um you know
what where where where did the random
fluctuations go
um
before i do that though just to note
that
all the the first
equality in equation one
is telling you
is that there is some probabilistic
relationship between x and x dot
that's all it's saying it says saying
that there is some coupling and normally
in terms of a causal coupling between a
function of x
and x dot so if you just think about our
previous conversation in terms of
generalized coordinates of motion and
everything coming along in pairs like
p's and q's in classical physics or
real and imaginaries in um in quantum
physics and this is why there's always a
pair of things
at least two things to worry about
because all that we're saying here is
that there's some relationship between
where you are and how you're moving
in state space and it's a probabilistic
relationship and so if you um if you
think about what that means in terms of
modeling things this is a state space
model so it tells you nothing about
which is the most likely state to be in
it just tells you how likely where am i
going to go from here
that's all it's all it's telling that's
all we know
so you can start to think now about um
the probability distributions are where
i will be in the future
um or you can think about probability
distributions um
over the trajectories or the paths that
you take and that's basically what
thomas was you know was highlighting
previously
um
in the free energy principle
the fokker plank is actually not used
very much
so i'm just saying
for blue's benefit you know she was
worried about the so fast and slow and
how does that fit into the focal plank
in fact
most of the interesting stuff comes from
the path integral formulation the the
vodka plank is you know does bring a lot
to the table
but only when you look at the solutions
to the focal plank equation that you
would get um under the assumption that
it has a solution and you get into
things like the helmholtz decomposition
and solenoidal flow and all that
interesting stuff and the link between
the steady state density over states and
the
um the dynamical coupling that
underwrites or defines the um the the
original orange van equation but
if you you can ignore all that if you
wanted to and just talk about
the probability distributions over paths
so no longer am i defining me
my homeostasis in terms of the states
that i occupy that's the side product
of the trajectories and the dynamics
that i typically convince when i'm in
this situation or at this point in state
space so i think the more powerful and
certainly the the basis of the free
energy um
principle the more powerful calculus is
actually in the pathetical formulation
so you can tell a free energy principle
story without even mentioning the vocal
plank
equation if you wanted to and really
that story is a story of um least action
or hamilton's principle of least action
so what does that mean it just means
that
one way of summarizing the behavior of
things or the characteristic behavior of
things
is in terms of the most likely way
forward from here the most likely
trajectory or path from this point
in state space
what is that it is the path of least
action what is that is nothing more than
the most likely path
what is the most likely path well it's
just given by the longevity equation the
flow operator the f of x
iterated in time in the absence or under
the most likely random fluctuations
so one of the most likely random
fluctuations well we just said that the
most the most likely random fluctuation
is zero
so all that we're doing is taking the
omega the random fluctuations
out of the equations of motion and that
just is the path of least action where
which is just the most likely path
um and if you apply the calculus of
variations
to
that notion you get these expressions
that in equation for here so the
if you interpret the action a
as the probability or the surprisal
or the negative log probability of a
particular path
then if you want to minimize the action
you're just
trying to identify the path that that is
most likely that is just the evolution
of the system without any random
fluctuations so the first
expression um
which follows a convention pursued in
this paper and other papers uh that
the paths of least action are namely the
most likely paths are in bold phase all
this says is the most likely path in
bulk phase
simply is that which renders that path
the most likely for this system which is
another way of saying that it minimizes
the action
what does that mean well it means if you
deviate from this path in any way
known as a variation and you know
variational calculus
if you vary or deviate from this path
then you are going to
increase the action so you can think of
a marble rolling down a long valley
and
the course of the marble
rolling down a long valley
will or will follow a trajectory that is
always at the minimum of the the height
of the valley
and therefore any deviation from that
path
will cause you to climb the sides of the
valley and therefore the path integral
or the average action perfect and the
average action
will be slightly bigger than the path of
least action
so that's basically what is meant by the
second implication which is that any
variation of the path about the path of
least action
will cause an increase in the uh action
um and another way of stating that is
that the path of least action at the
point of the minima infinitesimal
changes don't change the action because
you're at the flat bottom or
um
microscopically the valley has has
bottomed out and therefore um your
variation is zero
and
another way of expressing that is where
we started which is the path of least
action
follows a trajectory in the absence of
any random fluctuations which is just
the final equality down there so it's
just the original launch val equation
but without random fluctuations or with
the most likely
random fluctuations
so i brought on
as you saw this uh classical waddington
epigenetic landscape
here's the marble
rolling down a hill coming towards us
might we interpret decisions
as being bifurcations or
if we're talking about paths of least
action in space
or paths of least action on cognitive
parameters
where do
decisions come into play
that's definitely for blue that one
yep i knew it
so
can can we even make decisions i'm going
to just answer your question with a
question
uh um
because
i mean if if up until this point we are
just a sum of all the things that have
occurred
up up into this point you know we now
have a model
that that's based on all previous action
and when you come to this you know
bifurcating path
um you're just going to take the one
that that minimizes free energy right
like like isn't that how it goes
so according to your model and all the
things that have brought an organism to
that point
that's my answer
to it right i want thomas to answer now
but he can't he must use the words free
will
i'm not going there
i don't think philosophically qualified
enough to use those words i skipped
right over it but but but said it more
or less
anyone can address how is free will
related to free energy
or how decision making plays into a
path of least action
while thomas is gathering his thoughts
to slip free will in a non-philosophical
sense into his response i think that's
absolutely right so um
you know the notion of a bifurcation i
think is very prescient when you think
about uh paths of least action on any
energy landscape in particular free
energy landscape um
and
um
but at the same time we if we just
pursue the path of least action there
are no decisions or it looks as if there
are no decisions from a mathematical
point of view but in virtue of the fact
that
there is an indeterminacy about the
paths you would pursue
from the initial where you start say the
marble at the beginning of the top of
the hill here
that indeterminacy i think does call
into question uh whether um the uh
technically the
chaotic structure that underwrites the
itinerancy of the thing that we are
trying to model
will actually induce a sensitivity to
initial conditions which means that we
can never totally predict how we will
behave or the decisions we will make
given our state of mind and the state of
the world at the present time so i think
there is a latitude to talk about free
will
but
it would be uh of the kind that inherits
from
deterministic chaos and sensitivity to
initial conditions
and that's
that's quite important of framing it in
the context of bifurcations in
deterministic dynamical systems theory
it's quite an important move because of
course the longevity equation
does not admit deterministic chaos
because you've got random fluctuations
so you have stochastic chaos or you
could have stochastic chaos but you
can't have deterministic chaos
so the question now is um where does
deter
is there any opportunity for
deterministic chaos
um in the context of
the free energy
description of
sentient behavior and choice making and
i think there is
but only in a very special class of
systems where the internal the
particular states or the internal states
in the blanket states and don't have any
random fluctuations and you may be
asking well there must also have random
fluctuations well not necessarily at a
particular scale
if you take um a hundred million neurons
or say even a million neurons
and you now write down your state as the
average of a population or ensemble of
neurons
all the random fluctuations and neural
noise will be averaged away and this is
exactly the same
mechanics that thomas was talking about
before in terms of
the renormalization group and taking
certain mixtures
carefully to
eliminate fast fluctuations and random
fluctuations so the argument would be um
here if you want to talk about
bifurcations in the sense of
transcritical bifurcations or hot
bifurcations
as a way of describing a particular path
of least action
or
paths of least action from slightly
different um
initial conditions
then i think you'd have to you'd be
perfectly licensed to do that but you'd
have to
be very careful in saying that we are
assuming here
that the dynamics are deterministic and
therefore only apply at a particular
scale and they apply it at a scale where
the particular dynamics the internal and
blanket states don't possess any random
fluctuations of that matter
and that's quite interesting because um
there are other things that inherit from
that that assumption you know again
coming back to this notion of you know
different kinds of particles some very
very small particles like the single
cells that blue was talking about before
maybe so small as in number and in size
that you cannot average away
the random fluctuations and they would
not show any deterministic chaos
but there may be a a of course a grain
description of neuronal dynamics and
computational anatomy
that does actually acquire a
deterministic aspect a classical aspect
where you have an end body like problem
which will invariably show some kind of
deterministic chaos which means that
then you can get back to
one
form of um looking at or something that
might look like free will anyway now
thomas has had plenty of time to tell us
about the dynamics of free will
so i i noticed that um
[Music]
the way you framed that was in terms of
unpredictability and that
under the definition of free will you
were using there
uh it's things where
we wouldn't necessarily be able to
predict in advance how well a particular
or how a particular system would evolve
and i'm sure that will
please some philosophers and upset
many others
um
i don't have an alternative definition
that would
work better please everybody
[Music]
and
so i i suppose we've spoken really about
one side of things which is the the
deterministic aspect
and clearly that does become very
relevant at
larger and slower scales
and i suppose it's also interesting to
think about unpredictability when
stochastic
dynamics become much more important
so we certainly could think about
systems where there are multiple
plausible paths and where
and
whether or even a continuum of plausible
paths and
the particular path they end up taking
will depend upon
uh the the um
particular values that the fluctuations
take
during the course of that path
arguably if the fluctuations are
themselves just dynamical systems that
are deterministic but
occurring at a much faster scale it's
still not really an unpredictability of
a stochastic sort because ultimately
it's described by a deterministic
dynamical system
um which again brings us back to this
renormalization group idea
and it depends a little bit on your your
interpretation of what happens at the
slowest or so the fastest possible
scales
um when we
perform this renormalization operation
is the fastest scale something that is
genuinely random or is it something that
is
a sort of recursive
um
recursively faster deterministic
dynamics
and either way it may be that if
stochastic descriptions are most
appropriate at some scale of description
um
we can develop a form of
unpredictability both from things like
deterministic chaos and uncertainty over
initial conditions
but also potentially from the form of
the random fluctuations that happen
along the particular trajectory in
systems that have more randomness
involved
um clearly when we're doing
um
when we're trying to describe a real
system or a real brain and the decisions
people make
we clearly don't have access to every
part of our system um and
what every neuron in that brain is doing
so to some extent we're always dealing
with a partially stochastic system
and that feeds into how we might end up
modeling behavior in those kinds of
systems as well
so if we were trying to fit an active
inference style model to real behavior
or even simulated vapor often what we
end up doing is adding in a term to
account for some
uncertainty in the action selection or
uncertainty that we as experimenters
have
in the action someone might choose even
if we think we know what the expected
free energy they're going to calculate
is and how they're going to evaluate the
alternative paths they might choose
and
so that's just an acknowledgement that
if we don't know everything we don't
have a complete description of the
system then we have to
to some extent to allow for some
stochastic
parts of that of course that that
stochastic element may be purely the
uncertainty over the initial conditions
in a system that can exhibit chaotic
behavior and that bifurcates in various
different ways
awesome
we'll
continue on as we approach the end of
the dot one
and introduce something we had talked
about in terms of the markov blanket
previously but it's the particular
partition
so
how have other mechanics
addressed particles
and how does this
particle
framework
do something different and what does
that different framing enable
it's blue's turn or i could give a shot
why don't you go ahead daniel
okay
as a non-physicist my understanding is
that particles
have not been explicitly modeled this
way
and fields
or continua
have been
the norm
the particulate
description provided here
enables a principled approach to
separating figure from ground
from separating an entity that's being
tracked that's doing the movement
away from the entity that is not doing
the movement
in a sense
that would just be one
thought
which i would concur with very much you
know it's um
if you if you go back and think about
the physics you did at school
um
usually it will be focused on
the behavior of some idealized gas in
what they would call a heat bath or a
heat reservoir
and
really what the particular petition
brings to the table
are deep questions about how did that
heat path get there and the heat path
now stands in for blanket states and
what's beyond the heat path
the external states so you know
it is it is a move which i am not aware
of
being um attempted in any other branch
of physics so in quantum physics the
markov blanket or the thing that
contains the particle of interest
probabilistically speaking is usually
defined in terms of a screening of
potential in the functional form of that
potential leads to all the applications
of quantum electrodynamics that you
might encounter and i repeat um
in
thermodynamics people just talk about
you know there being some blanket states
in terms of a heat path but don't go
they don't think about what's beyond the
heat path
in terms of classical mechanics
um
perhaps there is a notion of particles
there which is less less um
less
if you like hidden under under the wrong
the rug um
but of course you uh don't have any
explicit representation of the internal
dynamics because normally
classical mechanics is just dealing with
you know the motion of heavenly bodies
or large massive objects without really
thinking about their
uh the faster dynamics that underwrite
um autonomous movement or animate
movement or what um people in chemistry
might refer to as active matter
just
a few thoughts on that the classical
indeed it does deal with diffusing
particles massive bodies but just like
you pointed out
it
doesn't consider internal states so it's
like a view from the outside and this is
a bit more like a view from both sides
which enables us to have sentient or
cognitive behavior on both sides of the
observation interface rather than
implicitly on only one side which is a
very different situation
and then you uh talked about in this
thermo
physics context and in this quantum
physics context like
what is beyond the boundary and
then uh in the quantum case you said
that that was like the role of the heat
bath and what's outside of it is the
schrodinger potential and what's outside
of it and that makes me think about
schrodinger's implicit question and
schrodinger's explicit question
schrodinger's explicit question in 1944
and in ramstead at all 2018 was what is
life
schrodinger's implicit question was what
is beyond
the quantum what is outside of that
and so
it's almost um
interesting though appropriate that the
particular partition
actually brings those two together
but i would let anyone else reflect to
how they're brought together
if anyone wants to add or we'll just
continue to leave a few little pieces
before closing the dot one
i was hoping that thomas and blue would
yeah he has an excellent observation uh
and i just wanted to reinforce it um so
in you know what is life
it's basically um coming back to our
early question it's um those it's those
systems that are equipped with a
homeostasis of sorts but beyond that
these things move so there is there are
homeostatic systems that are
self-constructing and self-maintaining
that move and this i think speaks to the
importance of having this the active
states that couple back and influence
the um the external states beyond the
markov blankets uh you know again
speaking to another important natural
kind the distinction between inert
particles and active particles um where
you've got this active autopoetic like
aspect to the maintenance of uh of the
homeostasis so you know
i think that's quite an important
observation that we're not talking about
we are talking about a bi-directional
exchange across the markov blanket um uh
just to reiterate your sort of
observation that what we're doing here
is trying to account for the coupling
between the inside and the outside of
something we're not just interested in
the inside as in classical physics or
the outside uh or what it looks like
from the outside in terms of um sorry
thermo
statistical mechanics or what it looks
like from the outside in terms of
classical mechanics we're actually
trying to get to the meat of the
maintenance of a markov blanket and
thickness in an active context
so then as a closing
round here i wanna
point to one tension that we
pulled in the dot zero
so here in footnote um 21
it says a lot of interesting things
but then it says minimization implies
the teleology that goes beyond any claim
of the fep
do particles minimize surprisal or free
energy well
minimization implies a teleology that
goes beyond any claim of the fep
okay very well
later
the question is asked is it tenable to
interpret gradient flows on variational
free energy as variational inference or
is this just teleological window
dressing
so
where is teleology
is
teleology
in the fep
or is it window dressing what's the
window what's the building what's
outside the building
is minimization
teleological
and is that in the fep's claims or what
other claims are coming to the table if
it's not part of fep in the strict sense
this is thomas's favorite question
i didn't know
my favorite question is that um in that
i've asked it before
several times
and what's lyrical about it
um
i mean it is a it is a
tricky question in this place i mean to
some extent the answer to the
big bold question is both
um
and i think
it's also worth asking the question is
it useful um so
the the reason we've spoken about it
quite a lot in the past and one of the
one of the reasons has come up is that
in some of the the recent formulations
we've dealt with in in some other papers
that we've been discussing
um is
that the free energy or the gradient
flows have been on some
normally steady state density
that can be interpretable as a
generative model of sorts or as a
marginal likelihood
and
now the the challenge is that a marginal
likelihood
in itself is not necessary or is it is i
suppose a special case of the free
energy
when the
variational density that we were
speaking about earlier you know this
tractable part of the optimization
problem um
is exactly equal to a true posterior
density once we've performed both in
infants
so
the question we've often asked is
whether
the
whether that's kale diversions whether
there's divergence between our
approximate distribution our variational
distribution and our
true exact bayesian solution
and
whether if that is defined stipulatively
as being zero whether there is a
meaningful
role of free energy minimization as
being interpretable as influence
and there are several possible answers
to that one is that
that
that we're really dealing with um
the
when we're when we're engaging in
computational neuroscience we're dealing
with a attractable approximation to how
systems behave so it's useful from the
perspective of a computational
neuroscientist to be able to write it
down into the free energy functional
and but not necessarily
treat that as a literal description of
what brains and sentient creatures are
doing in terms of the variation free
energy aspect
we could still interpret the marginal
likelihood
as before
or interpret graded flows and margin
likelihood as before
and another answer to it is that
part of
what makes inference work particularly
in a dynamical setting is not going to
the bottom of a free energy minimum but
it's finding a way of staying there
and so that depends upon the ability to
predict and the ability to represent
some dynamics of how a system's evolving
at time over time so it's a question of
staying at the bottom of the marble
staying at the bottom of the valley and
not deviating up the sides
and we could interpret that as a form of
inference as well and here we then deal
with
flows that are not necessarily up or
down
free energy gradients or marginal
likelihood gradients but are
maintaining the same level or staying at
the bottom of the valley and that's
often what we refer to in terms of the
solenoidal flows
and this links back to a lot of the
discussion we're having about
deterministic versus um
sort of chaotic dynamics i should call i
suppose deterministic chaos where um
systems can behave in a range of
different ways it's very different
difficult to capture if you're just
going up and down probability gradients
so it talks about how we go around
probability gradients how we circle
around the hill or or along the valley
and the potentially chaotic way that we
we do that
and that
results in a form of prediction it
results in a
a way of staying at the bottom of the
valley and not um not leaving it so we
could interpret that as a form of
imprints as well
and i think there probably are still
some open questions as to whether
whether um
under certain circumstances it looks as
if we are also minimizing this kale
divergence part this
divergence between the
[Music]
approximate and exact
basin posteriors
and i
i think that's still open i think
plausibly there will be ways of writing
things down that look as if they're
doing that
it may be that
it's
simply a useful approximation to how we
tend to um
a useful approximation that we can
tractably write down and simulate and
perform computational neuroscience with
the third possibility is that
if the brain is realized or evolved to
realize that things in the world behave
in the way we've been describing
it could plausibly be a mechanism or
variational inference type
approaches could be a mechanism that the
brain has evolved to use to model its
environment as well
um which would bring back this idea of
explicit variational free energy
and so i think there are several
different possibilities i think there's
still probably an ongoing discussion
about a lot of this
and for me the idea of inference and
variational inference has to be one
where the tail divergence is
decreasing over time
where uh it's not something that we
necessarily keep static
which might mean that variational
inference is is
um
not something that's necessarily
happening in the systems we've been
describing so far
um but whether it could be something
that could be interpreted in terms of
the flow of internal states towards
their most likely value and another
aspect of that
or whether it's simply a good
approximation
i'm sure carl will have other things to
say on this because i've not given a
definitive or a clear answer one way or
the other here
um for me variation influence occurs
when the kl divergence is shrinking
however you could also argue that
marginal likelihoods in the optimization
of marginal likelihood is itself a form
of bayesian inference and more akin to
sort of model selection
certainly it feeds into the idea of
active influence in terms of acting upon
the world to maximize
the
fit between the model of the world and
that that element is certainly there
excellent
and then blue will each have a last
thought and next week at the same time
we'll continue with 45.2 but for now
carl and then blue our
last thoughts on what thomas just added
or anything else
you know i think he's absolutely right
i mean i think it's more interesting to
ask the question isn't it um i i think
it's largely from the point of view of
the way the world works i think it's the
fep interpretation is largely
technological window dressing
but i think it's incredibly useful to
have that
cheap and cheerful and doable kind of
window dressing when you actually want
to build artifacts that behave
as creatures who are autopoetic and have
a homeostasis and have make the right
kinds of decisions
awesome
first thomas or carl any last thoughts
and then blue and then all clothes
just to say thank you for organizing
this and
inviting us to be part of it
blue
yeah it was great to have you guys here
and um i definitely had some questions
that um i've been wondering about for a
long time resolved so
um that was really great
yes this was an excellent discussion and
we sometimes think about the dot zero
as almost like preparing the marble i
don't know if it's blowing it out of
glass or just bringing it to the edge of
the bathtub and the dot zero we just
walk through
in the order as it was laid out and try
to follow the traces and understand some
of the causal dynamics at play behind
the writing and then in the dot one
we're in kind of like this plane and so
there's little micro variations some
local scents to be made but i really
appreciated how we opened up a lot of
threads and also covered a lot of the
key aspects of the paper
and then we'll be
looking forward to the dot too when we
get to climb or descend or
circumambulate and continue the
discussion so
thanks again to carl and thomas and all
the other authors for this great paper
and thank you blue and brock for the dot
zero
see you next week
bye
you